<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answere to a popish ryme, lately scattered abroad in the west parts, and much relyed vpon by some simply-seduced. By Samuel Hieron, minister of the word of God, at Modbury in Deuon</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119038</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854245</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1070:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answere to a popish ryme, lately scattered abroad in the west parts, and much relyed vpon by some simply-seduced. By Samuel Hieron, minister of the word of God, at Modbury in Deuon</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
                  <author>Marlorat, Augustin, 1506-1562. Catholike and ecclesiasticall exposition of the holy gospell after S. Marke and Luke.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Simon Stafford, dwelling in Hosier lane, neere Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Prints the whole of the "popish ryme", "A catholke and ecclesiasticall exposition of the holy gospell after S. Marke and Luke" (STC 17505, where other answers are listed), followed by the answer--STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Anſvvere to a Popiſh Ryme, lately ſcattered abroad in the Weſt parts, and much relyed vpon by ſome ſimply-ſeduced.</p>
            <p>By Samuel Hieron, Miniſter of the Word of God, at Modbury in Deuon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. 10, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beware of Men.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 3.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beware of Dogs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Simon Stafford, dwelling in Hoſier lane, neere Smithfield. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>To my much esteemed friend, J. L.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou will wonder, I am ſure (conſidering my profeſsion, to ſee me become a Poet. And indeed I do almoſt maruell at it my ſelfe, knowing my ſelfe to want the two principal furtherances of Poetry: the one is natures inſtinct <note n="a" place="margin">They ſay, <hi>Poëta naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> if a man be not, as it were, a Poet borne, hee ſhall neuer prooue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in that facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>, which God in his holy prouidence hath denyed me: the other is a certaine retired freedom from all ſuch buſineſſes, which may breed diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note n="b" place="margin">Carmina ſeceſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentis &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia quaerunt, Ouid. de Triſt.</note> which my publike Calling, beſides priuate encombrances, will not afford me. Yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, vpon this preſent occaſion, I haue euen forced my ſelfe to this ſtraiter courſe of Verſe-making, though I know, that for mine owne caſe (hauing to deale in ſuch a diſtempered and vnruly Subiect) that leſſe-limited &amp; freer kind of diſcourſe, which Proſe alloweth, had bene more conuenient: Becauſe the rules of Cadence, &amp; number (to which our Engliſh Poetry eſpecially is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fined) do many times ſo ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an vnaccuſtomed Practitioner, that he is in haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, either of obſcuring the ſence (which in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this nature were ſomething dangerous) or of marring the Verſe (which to the apprehenſion of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:19654:3"/>
common conceit were very ridiculous.) But howſoeuer I haue erred in the carriage of this verſe, I hope, to you and to others, whoſe fauour, eyther becauſe of their Iudgement, or their honeſty, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, this ſhall excuſe me: that meeting with our common Aduerſary (who appeareth ſometime in ſhape of a States-man, debating of Titles, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth affayres, <note n="c" place="margin">Witneſſe the Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libets, Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp;c.</note> ſometime as a Petitioner to the King and Parliament, <note n="d" place="margin">At the Kings firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, &amp; now ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> ſometime as a plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſwader, <note n="e" place="margin">Briſtowes Motiues, &amp; Bookes of that nature</note> ſometime as a Reſtorer of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Text, to the natiue purity thereof,<note n="f" place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. and Grego. Martin.</note> ſometime as a man of a very tender Conſcience, giuing reaſons why he cannot come to our Aſſemblies,<note n="g" place="margin">Howlet.</note> ſomtime as a Rayler at our gouernment, and an approuer of our open enemies; <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>The wardword.</hi> Quo teneam vultus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Protea nodo.</note> that, I ſay, meeting with this time-ſeruing <hi>Proteus,</hi> in the faſhion of a Rimer or Balladine, and crept in (as the maner of falſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. 2.4.</hi> Similes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent labra lactucas.</note>) into both the hands and the heartes of many ſimply-ſeduced; I haue endeuored to make the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuce like the lips (as the prouerb is) and to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion my ſelfe to him in verſing, to whom I am ſure (without wilful forſaking the playne truth of God, manifeſted in Scripture) I ſhall neuer be like in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing.</p>
            <p>The Seruice it ſelfe, which is heere ſent vs in by this Runnagate,<note n="k" place="margin">He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth hee was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant.</note> is for ſubſtance agreeing with the reſt of their Romiſh Cates, thogh (to ſay the truth)
<pb facs="tcp:19654:3"/>
it hath come through the hands of a very homely and ſluttiſh Cooke, by whom it is neyther ſeaſoned with wit or argument, no, nor yet ſet forth after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good ordinary faſhion: But it is euen a very Gally-mawfrey, of certayne naked and indigeſted Allegations (as it were the leauings and ſcraps of ſome other) without eyther order or proofe, as though euery Papiſt were a Pope, and euery word of his mouth an Oracle. Belike the Slouen thought it good enough for thoſe, for whom it was proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as indeed it is: for thoſe which turne their eares from the trueth, and are giuen vnto fables <note n="l" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.4.</note>; and by ſome, vpon my knowledge (to whome, I feare me, God hath ſent ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould beleeue lyes) it is highly magnified,<note n="m" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.11.</note> as a ſpeciall Preſeruatiue againſt ſuppoſed Hereſie, and as a well-framed Sconce, which none of vs all is able to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow.</p>
            <p>In regard whereof, knowing my ſelfe bound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others to contend earneſtly for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Fayth, <note n="n" place="margin">Iude 3.</note> I haue vndertaken this which you here ſee. For my deſire and true intent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it is beſt knowne to him which ſeeth in ſecret<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 6.4.</note>, and in his due time will make the counſels of all hearts manifeſt. <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the thing it ſelfe, how it is, and how well it is, I ſubmit it to the cenſure of the godly-wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19654:4"/>
praying them, that with their fauourable (if not allowance, yet at leaſt) conniuence, it may paſſe to the vſe of thoſe, to whom it is intended: And among others, I haue directed it eſpecially to you, in part of recompence for a great deale of kindneſſe, entreating you to entertayne it with the like mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of loue, wherewith it is offered. And ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God to fill you with the fruites of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 1.11.</note> I commend you to his grace in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Modbury,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 20. 1604.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your very louing friend, <hi>SAM. HIERON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Papiſts Ryme.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Pray thée, Proteſtant, heare with mée,<note n="a" place="margin">Indeede a man had need to be very patient, that meaneth to heare thee.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To aſke thée Queſtions two or thrée:</l>
               <l>And if an anſwere thou canſt make,</l>
               <l>More of thy counſell I will take. <note n="b" place="margin">Yet I feare, that thogh thou were brayed in a Morter with a Peſtell, among Wheat, thy foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe will not depart from thee: Pro. 27.22.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Many ſundry Sects appeare,</l>
               <l>Now in the world farre and neere,</l>
               <l>The Caluiniſt, the Proteſtant,</l>
               <l>The Zuinglian, the Puritant:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Browniſt, and the Family of Loue,</l>
               <l>And many more which I can proue,</l>
               <l>And the Romane fayth truely,</l>
               <l>Which you call Papiſtry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And euery one confeſſe IESV,</l>
               <l>Saying that their Fayth is true:</l>
               <l>But amongſt theſe tell mee how,</l>
               <l>The Trueth from fayned lyes to know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All theſe in very deede,</l>
               <l>Rehearſe all Articles in the Creede,</l>
               <l>And euery one of them ſayth,</l>
               <l>That theirs is the Catholique Fayth:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this it is that I doe ſéeke, <note n="c" place="margin">I beleeue, thou art one of thoſe, which are euer learning, &amp; neuer come to the knowledge of the Trueth, 2. Tim. 3.7. Take the Lanterne which Dauid vſed, and thou ſhalt ſoone finde the true Church, Pſal. 119.105.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To knowe the Church Catholique,</l>
               <l>The Communion or Company</l>
               <l>Of holy men in Vnity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Catholike.</head>
               <l>IN your Bible I haue read,</l>
               <l>The Church muſt through the world bee ſpred:</l>
               <l>For Chriſt he his Apoſtles ſent</l>
               <l>With power and Commaundement,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That to all Nations they ſhould goe,</l>
               <l>To preach and to baptize alſo.</l>
               <l>Who hath done this? to know I will,</l>
               <l>For that is ſure the Church of Chriſt. <note n="d" place="margin">I hope thou wilt not ſay that Rome hath don this: the charge was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and vndertaken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Rome was conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:5"/>
               <l>As for example, let mee know,</l>
               <l>And if thou canſt I pray thée ſhow,</l>
               <l>What Church did take in hand</l>
               <l>The firſt conuerſion of this Land?<note n="e" place="margin">The Apoſtles Church for ought you can proue to the contrary.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And all other countries euery where,</l>
               <l>Throughout the world farre and neere:<note n="f" place="margin">Who but a Papiſt, would dare to ſay this?</note>
               </l>
               <l>If this were not the Church of Rome,</l>
               <l>Then will I be conuerted ſoone.<note n="g" place="margin">You build your Faith vpon a very ſure grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Saint Paul in his Epiſtle fayth,<note n="h" place="margin">Did Paul ſay that Rome ſhould neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Fayth?</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Romanes had the Catholique Fayth,</l>
               <l>Saying it was renowned,</l>
               <l>Spoken of, or publiſhed</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Through the world, ouer all,</l>
               <l>Catholique, Vniuerſall:</l>
               <l>And if your Churches were euen ſo,<note n="i" place="margin">Our Church is a part of the Catholique Church, diſproue it if you can.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then to your Churches I would go.<note n="k" place="margin">You may come to our Churches, the Pope gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you leaue, ſo that you keepe your heartes to him.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Prophets.</head>
               <l>SO ſayth the Prophet Malachy,</l>
               <l>There ſhould be offred farre and nye,</l>
               <l>A cleane Oblation or Sacrifice,<note n="l" place="margin">When you read, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and Sacrifice, you thinke ſtrait that makes for the Maſſe, not know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, or not ſeeming to know the language of the Scripture.</note>
               </l>
               <l>From place where now the Sun doeth riſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To the going downe of the ſame.</l>
               <l>And what is that, I pray thée name?</l>
               <l>If it be not the holy Maſſe,</l>
               <l>I will be a Proteſtant as I was.<note n="m" place="margin">If thou hadſt bene of vs, thou wouldeſt haue continued with vs, 1. Iob. 2.19.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In the eightéenth Pſalme I found,</l>
               <l>The whole world ſhould heare their ſound,<note n="n" place="margin">Namely, of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and their doctrine; proue our Doctrine to diſagree with theirs.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And it this marke you doe not want,</l>
               <l>Preſently I will recant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Continuance.</head>
               <l>THis is another marke moſt ſure,</l>
               <l>The Fayth of Chriſt muſt ſtill endure,<note n="o" place="margin">Chriſtes Fayth muſt endure, therfore Rome is the true Church. A hote Argument.</note>
               </l>
               <l>According as our Sauiour ſayd,</l>
               <l>When for Saint Peter hee had prayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:5"/>
               <l>Simon, thy Fayth ſhall neuer fayle,</l>
               <l>The gates of Hell ſhall not preuayle,</l>
               <l>The holy Ghoſt your Comforter,</l>
               <l>Shall remayne with you for euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And I my ſelfe, your ſureſt friend,</l>
               <l>Will be with you vnto the end.</l>
               <l>Saint Paul hath the like ſpeach,</l>
               <l>There ſhall be alwayes men to preach,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Apoſtles, <note n="p" place="margin">Some ſay they are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and are not, Re. 2.2.</note> Doctours, and the like,</l>
               <l>In the Church Catholike:</l>
               <l>If this be not the Church of Rome, <note n="q" place="margin">Becauſe you ſay it, we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleeue it.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then will I be conuerted ſoone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Viſible.</head>
               <l>ANother marke there is moſt cleare,</l>
               <l>The Church of God muſt ſtill appeare,</l>
               <l>As a City on a hill,<note n="r" place="margin">Some wreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, 2. Pet. 3.16. Take heed.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Seene and continue ſtill;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As a light on a Candleſticke,</l>
               <l>So is the Church Catholique.</l>
               <l>Our Sauiour ſayth, If one offend,</l>
               <l>And will not be ruled by his friend,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell all the Church without delay:<note n="s" place="margin">Would you haue vs go to Rome with euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt? it ſeemeth ſo; for you tye the Church to that See.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And if he will not then obay,</l>
               <l>Doe thou eſtéeme ſuch a man,</l>
               <l>An Heathen or a Publican.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is not that the Church, wherein we ſée</l>
               <l>Two hundred Biſhops thirty thrée,</l>
               <l>To haue ſuccéeded each other,</l>
               <l>Since the time of Saint Peter?<note n="t" place="margin">You muſt firſt prooue that Saint Peter was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shew mee this marke in you,<note n="u" place="margin">Thou thy ſelfe ſayſt, there haue bene ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely 63. Biſhops in England, ſince Peter: then eyther ours is the true Church, or elſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops is no ſure marke.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And I will ſay your Fayth is true:</l>
               <l>If this be not in the Fayth of Rome,</l>
               <l>Then will I be conuerted ſoone.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:6"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Vnity.</head>
               <l>ANother marke there is truly,</l>
               <l>The Church muſt haue Vnity,</l>
               <l>As our Sauiour hath foretold,</l>
               <l>One Shepheard and one Fold:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One is my Spouſe, one is my Loue,</l>
               <l>One is my Darling and my Doue:</l>
               <l>This is his Spouſe, and at ſome time</l>
               <l>He doeth reſemble it to a Vine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Father is the Huſbandman,</l>
               <l>A Branch is euery Chriſtian,</l>
               <l>This is his Body Myſticall,</l>
               <l>The which he doeth his Kingdome call:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereof Saint Peter had the Keyes,<note n="w" place="margin">What became of the Keyes, when Pope Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us 2. threw them into Tibur.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And his Succeſſors haue alwayes:<note n="x" place="margin">As though no body did ſucceede Peter, but the Pope, who is rather the ſucceſſour of Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, then Peter, as Pope Hadrian the fourth ſaid when he dyed.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And likewiſe Saint Paul ſayth,</l>
               <l>One Baptiſme and one Fayth,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And one Lord IESV:</l>
               <l>Haue no diſſention among you.</l>
               <l>If this be not the Church of Rome,</l>
               <l>Then will I be conuerted ſoone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Holy.</head>
               <l>THis you ſay in very déede,</l>
               <l>When you rehearſe the holy Créede,<note n="y" place="margin">So you ſay in the Creede, that Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God, and yet you ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, he is in body preſent at the Maſſe.</note>
               </l>
               <l>One Church Catholique,</l>
               <l>Holy and Apoſtolique.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is another marke truely,</l>
               <l>The Church of God muſt be holy:</l>
               <l>Holy men, Holy Seruice,</l>
               <l>Ceremonies, Sacrifice:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sacraments and Holy dayes,</l>
               <l>Are obſerued in her alwayes:</l>
               <l>As for the Saints and Martyrs all,</l>
               <l>And Virgins, which you Saynts doe call;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:6"/>
               <l>I aſke you when they liued and where,</l>
               <l>Whoſe names are in your Calender:</l>
               <l>In what Religion they dyed,</l>
               <l>By whom they were Canonized?<note n="z" place="margin">Who made the Pope a Saint-maker?</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Proue that theſe agrée with you,</l>
               <l>And I will ſay your Fayth is true:</l>
               <l>If they were not your company,<note n="a" place="margin">You ſtand ſo much vpon Company, that you will rather goe to the Deuill, then want Company.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then is your Fayth an Hereſy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Heretikes.</head>
               <l>OVr Sauiour warneth vs to haue care,</l>
               <l>Of falſe Prophets to beware,<note n="b" place="margin">That makes vs take heed of you.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which in his name ſhall come,</l>
               <l>Not ſent, yet they ſhall runne:<note n="c" place="margin">There bee many of your Church come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs to work miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, before you bee ſent for.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Théeues, not entring by the Doore,<note n="d" place="margin">A liuely deſcription of the Popes Clergy.</note>
               </l>
               <l>That kill and ſteale and kéepe a ſtoore,</l>
               <l>Woolues in Shepheards clothing,</l>
               <l>That kill the Soule, and ſteale the tithing,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dogges, Foxes, and Maſters of lyes,</l>
               <l>That newe Sects will deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Bringing in diſſention,</l>
               <l>And heape thouſands to perdition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where haue you bene this many a yere,</l>
               <l>That none of you durſt once appeare?</l>
               <l>Euer ſince our Sauiours time,</l>
               <l>To whom did your Light ſhine?<note n="e" place="margin">To thoſe which had eyes to ſee it.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where did your principall Paſtor ſit?<note n="f" place="margin">In Heauen.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Who kept your keyes, who fed your ſhéep?<note n="g" place="margin">You haue butchered a good ſort of them.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Shew ſome Churches you haue built:</l>
               <l>I can ſhew many you haue ſpilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How might a man haue found you out,</l>
               <l>To haue tryall in a matter of doubt:<note n="h" place="margin">You be too proud to learne: It is the firſt leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you teach your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, to admit no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Where for ſo many a yeere</l>
               <l>No ſuch company did appeare?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:7"/>
               <l>Vntill Luther, a lying Fryer, <note n="i" place="margin">If Luther had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a true Frier, he had neuer bene good.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Vpon whom the Deuill had deſire,</l>
               <l>Brake his vowe, <note n="k" place="margin">Herods vow is better broken then kept.</note> and marryed a Nunne.</l>
               <l>And there your Sect <note n="l" place="margin">Our Sect is the ſame that Pauls was, Act. 28.22.</note> firſt begun, <note n="m" place="margin">Eyther thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt this to be a lye, or thou knoweſt nothing.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And fauoured in Saxony</l>
               <l>By a Duke that loued liberty:</l>
               <l>And in King Edwards time truely, <note n="n" place="margin">There were Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in England, who bare witneſſe to this truth, by ſuffering death for it long afore King Edwards time.</note>
               </l>
               <l>It firſt infected our Country.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For a thouſand yeres you ſay,</l>
               <l>That Papiſtry did beare the ſway:</l>
               <l>And during all that ſpace,</l>
               <l>No Proteſtant durſt ſhew his face. <note n="o" place="margin">The more they lay hid the greater was your Tyranny.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who kept <note n="p" place="margin">Indeed you kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo faſt, that the people could haue no comfort by them.</note> the holy Scriptures then</l>
               <l>From the hands of wicked men?</l>
               <l>Who had authority to ordayne,</l>
               <l>Our Prieſts and Biſhops agayne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he that entreth without Order,</l>
               <l>As a thiefe doeth kill and murder.</l>
               <l>And one thing maketh me to muſe,</l>
               <l>That no Prieſt you doe refuſe, <note n="q" place="margin">A very tale.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Being ordred by the Church of Rome,</l>
               <l>But he was accepted ſoone:</l>
               <l>If he would ſay the newe Seruice,</l>
               <l>He ſhould haue a Benefice,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Without any further order,</l>
               <l>And accounted for the better: <note n="r" place="margin">He that hath once bin an eger Papiſt, &amp; is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted truly, is to be the better thought of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hauing known the abomination of Popery, hee muſt needs deteſt it more.</note>
               </l>
               <l>How can ſhée make a lawfull Prieſt,</l>
               <l>If ſhée be not the Church of Chriſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Anſwere this, O Proteſtant,</l>
               <l>If thou canſt, I will recant, <note n="s" place="margin">I beleeue you wil not be ſo good as your word</note>
               </l>
               <l>But while an anſwere you deuiſe, <note n="t" place="margin">A man need not bee long in making you an anſwere.</note>
               </l>
               <l>I counſell all men that are wiſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To hold the fayth mayntained heere,</l>
               <l>The ſpace of a thouſand yeere,</l>
               <l>Brought vnto vs Engliſhmen</l>
               <l>By our Apoſtle, <note n="u" place="margin">Who made him an Apoſtle?</note> Saint Auſten,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Who from Rome was biſher ſent.</l>
               <l>When Ethelbert was King of Kent,</l>
               <l>Who learned his fayth of Gregory, <note n="w" place="margin">This Gregory ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted him the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of Antichriſt, who ſo ſhould ſeeke to bee called Vniuerſall Biſhop: from this fayth you are gone.</note>
               </l>
               <l>His fayth was kept ſucceſſiuely,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By threeſcore Biſhops and thrée,</l>
               <l>Since Saint Peters time truely,</l>
               <l>Who learned his fayth of Chriſt Ieſu,</l>
               <l>Who is the Sonne of God moſt true.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Proteſtants <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> May not (Papiſt) ſuffer thée,</l>
               <l>Becauſe thy Queſtions idle bée:</l>
               <l>And if my counſell thou wilt take,</l>
               <l>Then heare the Anſwere I will make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou tell'ſt of Sects that doe appeare,</l>
               <l>And ſéemſt the truth glad to enquire:</l>
               <l>But euen in this I malice ſmell,</l>
               <l>And ſee thy ſpitefull meaning well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When thou theſe diuers ſects doeſt name,</l>
               <l>Thou would'ſt therby our Church defame, <note n="a" place="margin">I haue reaſon ſo to thinke, becauſe the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of ſuppoſed ſects amongſt vs, is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Imputation. See Briſt. Motiues, pag. 10.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And make fooles think that we them lou'd,</l>
               <l>When as with vs th'are not approu'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We doe not hang on Caluins ſléeue,</l>
               <l>Nor yet on Zuinglius we beléeue:</l>
               <l>And Puritanes we doe defye,</l>
               <l>If right the name you doe apply. <note n="b" place="margin">Viz. If eyther by that name, are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thoſe ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, called Cathari, who dreamed of a ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life: or elſe ſuch factious ones among vs, which haue ſoght the ſpoyle &amp; hauocke of the Church.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:8"/>
               <l>All giddy Sects among vs crept,</l>
               <l>We wiſh out of our Church were ſwept:</l>
               <l>No name doe we delight in more,</l>
               <l>Then that at Antioch giuen of yore. <note n="c" place="margin">Chriſtians, Act. 11.26</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now what ſects you Papiſts haue,</l>
               <l>I doe but thy owne witneſſe craue:</l>
               <l>Some Capucines, ſome Franciſcanes,</l>
               <l>And ſome bee called Dominicanes:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some Ieſuites, ſome Seculars, <note n="d" place="margin">The emulation &amp; dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt theſe 2. their Quodlibets doe ſhew.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Some gray, ſome black, ſome white Friars:</l>
               <l>And that your ſtore may not be ſpent,</l>
               <l>New Locuſts ſtill from Hell are ſent. <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <p>Reu. 9.3. Thoſe Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts doe well repreſent the Popes Clergy: they were bred of the ſmoke of the Pit; ſo are theſe of Hereſy, Ignorance, and Superſtition: they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the fruites of the earth; ſo theſe ſpoyle the Church.</p>
                     <p>The reaſon why the Church is called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</p>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou ſayſt, thou wouldſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church find out,</l>
               <l>So that I ſée thou art in doubt:</l>
               <l>And ſo indeede Vncertaynty</l>
               <l>Is ſtill the fruite of Popery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Catholike.</head>
               <l>IN our Bible thou haſt read.</l>
               <l>Tis well in ours, for yours is fled,</l>
               <l>And lurketh in a tongue vnuſde,</l>
               <l>Whereby poore people are abuſde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Church is Catholike, as you ſay,</l>
               <l>And ſo ſay we: but why, I pray?</l>
               <l>Becauſe to it, it were diſgrace,</l>
               <l>To limit it to time or place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It euer was, and ſo ſhall be,</l>
               <l>Since Chriſt, excluding no degrée: <note n="f" place="margin">Col. 3.11. Acts 10.34, 35.</note>
               </l>
               <l>It once was tyed vnto the Iewes,</l>
               <l>But now no place <note n="g" place="margin">Auſtine ſayth, it is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, becauſe ſpred o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the world, Ep. 170. and thereto agreeth the Scripture, Acts 1.8.</note> it doth refuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is a very fond ſurmiſe,</l>
               <l>Which you the Papiſts doe deuiſe,</l>
               <l>To ſhut the Church within Rome wall,</l>
               <l>And yet to call it generall. <note n="h" place="margin">Catholike and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral are all one; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one of their owne Councels ſayeth, The Romane Church is not the Vniuerſall Church, but of the Vniuerſall Church, Baſil. Con. ſy. 3</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:8"/>
               <l>The very name which you pretend.</l>
               <l>Whereby your Church you would defend,</l>
               <l>To all which doe the meaning know,</l>
               <l>Doth quite your fancy ouerthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You ſay, the charge, which Chriſt once gaue,</l>
               <l>The Romiſts well performed haue:</l>
               <l>But marke how thou thy ſelfe doeſt hurt,</l>
               <l>And lay Romes honour in the curt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That charge <note n="i" place="margin">Viz. of preaching tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the world.</note> was giuen firſt to them,</l>
               <l>Which liued at Ieruſalem, <note n="k" place="margin">The Apoſtles, Mat. 28. Acts 1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And thence the Goſpel iſſued out, <note n="l" place="margin">Acts 8.1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>As Eſay told <note n="m" place="margin">Iſai. 2.3.</note> the world throughout.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By them the Nations turned were, <note n="n" place="margin">We read in Hiſtories, as in Euſebius &amp; others, how the Apoſtles deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into al the quarters of the world.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And thence of Chriſt Rome firſt did heare:</l>
               <l>Yet now the place <note n="o" place="margin">Ieruſalem.</note> which others call'd,</l>
               <l>To Turkiſh Empire is inthrall'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So though 'twere true, which is not ſo,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſhalbe prou'd, I know,</l>
               <l>That Rome to Chriſt the nations brought,</l>
               <l>Yet this your reaſon were ſtarke nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now (perhaps) Rome doth, youle ſay,</l>
               <l>Bring home the wanderers to the way.</l>
               <l>In déed the Spaniards louing Gold,</l>
               <l>Haue brought the Indians to your fold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Frogs from Euphrates come out, <note n="p" place="margin">Euphrates was a great Riuer running neere the olde Babylon in Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea, &amp; was the defence of the City. Cyrus and Darius could neuer take the City, vntil by policy they dryed vp the riuer. Now in a ſpiritual ſence it doeth ſignify the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wealth and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Rome, which hath of later yeeres de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed exceedingly, and doth daily; &amp; the frogs, mentioned in Apoc. 16.13. doe well reſemble the Ieſuites, who feeling Euphrates to dry vp, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre themſelues, &amp; are croaking like Frogs in euery corner, labouring to maintayne the Popes authority.</note>
               </l>
               <l>I meane, the Ieſuited Rout</l>
               <l>Do ſpread themſelues in each country,</l>
               <l>To draw men to diſloyalty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They counſell Subiects kill their kings,</l>
               <l>Stabbings they vſe and poyſonings. <note n="q" place="margin">Our Countrey and times afford ſtore of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to proue this.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Chriſt gaue no ſuch commaundement,</l>
               <l>When firſt he his Diſciples ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of this Conuerſion, if you boaſt,</l>
               <l>Whereby, poore ſoule, Hell hath engroſt,</l>
               <l>I yéeld you full willyngly,</l>
               <l>It well agréeth with Popery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:9"/>
               <l>To draw Diſciples is no marke,</l>
               <l>For ſo doeth many a fayned Clarke.<note n="r" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.1, 2. Acts 20.30.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Church to trueth which doeth conuert,</l>
               <l>We doe imbrace with all our heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou ſayſt, Romes Fayth once ouer all</l>
               <l>The world was famous (ſo ſayth Paul)<note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And Rome did firſt conuert our Land,</l>
               <l>And hereupon you greatly ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Romes Fayth indéede once bare the bell,</l>
               <l>And ſo it did deſerue it well:</l>
               <l>But Rome's not now as heretofore;</l>
               <l>The faythfull City's made a whoore.<note n="t" place="margin">If. 1.21. So it was ſaid of Ieruſalem, which had more excellent particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar promiſes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome can alledge any.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If new Rome now, were as the old,</l>
               <l>Then we with Romaniſts would hold.</l>
               <l>If Rome become Chriſts enemy,</l>
               <l>Then we from Babylon muſt flye.<note n="u" place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſay that Rome is therefore ſound,</l>
               <l>Becauſe of old it was renownd,</l>
               <l>It may a Papiſt ſatiſfie:</l>
               <l>But men of iudgement it denye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Paul neuer Rome did magnifie,</l>
               <l>As he did thoſe of Theſſaly: <note n="w" place="margin">See 1. Theſ. 1.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Yet now that Church is cleane defac'd,</l>
               <l>And there the Turk himſelfe hath plac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Aſian Churches, <note n="x" place="margin">Epheſus, Smyrna, Pergamus, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia, Leodicea, Apoc. 1.11.</note> famous once,</l>
               <l>Are turned to an heape of ſtones:</l>
               <l>The golden lights <note n="y" place="margin">Thoſe ſeuen Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were repreſented by ſeuen golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, Apoc. 1.20.</note> of Saint Iohns age,</l>
               <l>Are now become euen Sathans Cage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Proue thou, that Rome hath not declinde</l>
               <l>From th'ancient Church by Paul refinde:</l>
               <l>And then Ile ſay, thou haſt done more,</l>
               <l>Then euer Papiſt did before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for firſt turning of our Nation,</l>
               <l>I trow thou nameſt it but for faſhion:</l>
               <l>For they that looke in Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>Thereof can find no certainty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Simon Zelotes, as ſome ſay, <note n="z" place="margin">Niceph. lib. 2. cap. 40.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Did firſt Chriſts Goſpell here diſplay,</l>
               <l>Euen whileſt that Emperour did raigne,</l>
               <l>By whom our Sauiour Chriſt was ſlayne. <note n="a" place="margin">Gildas Lib. de victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Aurelij Ambroſij.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some ſay, that he of Arimathy, <note n="b" place="margin">Ioſeph, who buryed Chriſt.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In the yeere of grace ſixty thrée,</l>
               <l>From France by Philip <note n="c" place="margin">Philip the Apoſtle.</note> was ſent ouer,</l>
               <l>To vs the Fayth for to diſcouer. <note n="d" place="margin">So ſayth Gildas alſo.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hereto agréeth a learned man,</l>
               <l>That ancient Clarke Tertullian,</l>
               <l>That by th' Apoſtles, Brittanny</l>
               <l>Was turn'd to Chriſtianity. <note n="e" place="margin">Tertullian in his book againſt the Iewes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other places co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted by the Apoſtles, reckoneth diuers partes of France, and of Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne: So doth Origene Hom. 4. vpon Ezekiel.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pope Eleutheriuo long agoe, <note n="f" place="margin">About the yeere of Chriſt, 180.</note>
               </l>
               <l>As his Epiſtle plaine doth ſhow, <note n="g" place="margin">This Epiſtle hath bin found out of the ancient records of the Kings of England.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto king Lucius hither ſent,</l>
               <l>Ere Ethelbert was king of Kent.<note n="h" place="margin">Which was about 600. yeres after Chriſt.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We hold the Fayth that then was taught:</l>
               <l>But you the ſame do ſet at naught:<note n="i" place="margin">Eleutherius referred <hi>K.</hi> Lucius to the Scriptures, clean againſt the Papiſts courſe now, and called him Gods Vicar in his kingdome: which Title, the Pope alone doeth now challenge.</note>
               </l>
               <l>When Rome the Trueth doth once forſake,</l>
               <l>Then we of Rome our leaues muſt take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If that our Church were Catholicke,</l>
               <l>To come to Church thou wouldſt not ſticke.</l>
               <l>If of the word thou knewſt the ſenſe,</l>
               <l>Thou ſoone would'ſt leaue that fond prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Church that Truth doth firme imbrace,</l>
               <l>Which all thoſe hold in euery place,</l>
               <l>Who leauing mens Traditions cleane,</l>
               <l>Vpon the Scriptures onely leane.<note n="k" place="margin">That is truly Catholike which euery where, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, &amp; by all (viz. true Chriſtians) is beleeued, Vincent. cont. Haer. cap. 3. Let Papiſts proue that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word Catholike being take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that ſence, ours is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholike church,</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Prophet.</head>
               <l>THou cit'ſt a Text of Malachy,<note n="l" place="margin">Mal. 1.11.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Hoping to prooue thy Maſſe thereby.</l>
               <l>Alas, the reaſon is but ſmall,</l>
               <l>And helpes that Idol not at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:10"/>
               <l>In it God threateneth the Iewes,</l>
               <l>Who their great Priuiledge did abuſe,</l>
               <l>And thought the Lord was tyed to them,</l>
               <l>And vnto their Ieruſalem.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Prophet telles, that God elſewhere</l>
               <l>Will find out thoſe, which ſhall him feare,</l>
               <l>And in an order without blame,</l>
               <l>Shall call vpon his holy Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Speaking to their capacity,</l>
               <l>The Legall termes he doth apply: <note n="m" place="margin">So Ioel 2.28. the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt foretelling the plenty of ſpirituall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightening, which the people ſhall haue vnder Chriſt, doeth deliuer it vnder the names of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and dreames, which notwithſtanding were not ordinary in the times of the Goſpell,</note>
               </l>
               <l>And calls our Goſpel-like Seruice,</l>
               <l>A pure <note n="n" place="margin">Pure in Chriſt, being accepted of GOD, through him, 1. Pet. 2.5</note> and ſpotleſſe Sacrifice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ground is here then for the Maſſe?</l>
               <l>It ſtil remayneth as it was:</l>
               <l>A groſſe deuice, defaming Chriſt,</l>
               <l>Who is our true and onely Prieſt.<note n="o" place="margin">See more of this here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, in ſpeaking more directly of the Maſſe.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſpeach of Dauid of the Skyes, <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 19.3. But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their account Pſal. 18.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto the Apoſtles, Paul applyes,<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſayth, their ſound went farre and neere,</l>
               <l>As in the ſtories doeth appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell mee, I pray, what good to you,</l>
               <l>This place you haue alledg'd can doe?</l>
               <l>It maketh nought for Popery,</l>
               <l>Or for your idle trumpery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Indéed th' infamous Fame is ſpred,</l>
               <l>Of Antichriſt your hideous head:</l>
               <l>And all Gods children him doe ſée,</l>
               <l>The man of ſinne <note n="r" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.3.</note> alone to bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th' Apoſtles Faith was farre diſperſt,</l>
               <l>And heere in England was reherſt.</l>
               <l>Sith then our doctrine is the ſame,</l>
               <l>To it belongs part of their fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:10"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Continuance.</head>
               <l>YOu ſay, Chriſts Fayth muſt ſtill endure.</l>
               <l>I yéeld that nothing is more ſure:</l>
               <l>And alwayes God a Church will haue,</l>
               <l>Though thereat Sathan rage and raue.<note n="s" place="margin">Math. 16.18.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It glads my hart, that Chriſt hath prayd:</l>
               <l>Thereby I know my Fayth is ſtayd:<note n="t" place="margin">Luke 22.32.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Comfort of Gods holy Sprite,</l>
               <l>Is eche good Chriſtians ſole delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This prooues there ſtill a Church ſhal bée,</l>
               <l>And herein thou and I agrée:</l>
               <l>To prooue the Church tyed to one Sea,</l>
               <l>Requireth yet a better Plea.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Fayth of Chriſt may ſtyll abide,</l>
               <l>Though Rome ſhould into Tibur ſlide:</l>
               <l>Gods ſpirit is frée, and is not bound <note n="v" place="margin">Iohn 3.8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Within the Liſts of Romiſh ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When thou canſt proue by holy writ,</l>
               <l>Chriſts Fayth to Rome by Charter knit,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall thy tale ſome credit find,</l>
               <l>Where now it turneth all to wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet Continuance is a Note</l>
               <l>Of Gods true Church: &amp; Paul hath wrote,</l>
               <l>That there ſhould ſtill ſome teachers be:<note n="w" place="margin">Eph. 4.11. &amp;c.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In Rome we this fulfilled ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſay, Continuance is no ſigne,</l>
               <l>To proue a Church to be diuine;</l>
               <l>We may not thinke eche doctrine ſure,</l>
               <l>Which doth for many yeeres endure.<note n="x" place="margin">It is true, that the truth ſhall continue, but yet it holdes not backwarde, that whatſoeuer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth, is Trueth. The Deuill is a lyer from the beginning.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Muſt not the Tares be let to grow,</l>
               <l>Till it be time the corne to mowe?<note n="y" place="margin">Math. 13.30.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And Antichriſt ſhall long time ſtay,</l>
               <l>Euen till the very Iudgement day.<note n="z" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.8.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:11"/>
               <l>The Arrian Hereſie yeeres did ſtand,</l>
               <l>Two hundred more then one thouſand: <note n="a" place="margin">Yea, and it was ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally receyued, that it was ſayd, the whole world was become an Arrian.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſo ſince Mahomet firſt was ſéene,</l>
               <l>A thouſand yeeres haue nombred béene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Romes name endures, but Rome is chang'd,</l>
               <l>And hath from Chriſt it ſelfe eſtrang'd:</l>
               <l>Quit thou Rome from Apoſtacy,</l>
               <l>Or name not perpetuity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pauls wordes do prooue, <note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 4.11, &amp;c.</note> that certeinly</l>
               <l>The Church ſhall haue a Miniſtry,</l>
               <l>And that there ſhalbe ſome to féed</l>
               <l>The Flocke of Chriſt at euery néed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But that theſe Paſtors here or there,</l>
               <l>Shall alwayes ſit in beautie cléere,</l>
               <l>This fond Conceipt, not one poore word,</l>
               <l>The holy Scripture doth affoord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In déed in Rome there diuers bée,</l>
               <l>That beare the name of Prelacy:</l>
               <l>Better we Pilates may them call,</l>
               <l>Séeking the Churches funerall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You call your Pope a Shepheard great:</l>
               <l>But where is his Spirituall Meate?</l>
               <l>I do not heare that hee doth preach:</l>
               <l>That would his greatnes much impeach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such are his carnall Cardinals,</l>
               <l>Or rather bloudy Canibals, <note n="c" place="margin">The people, that liue vpon mans fleſh.</note>
               </l>
               <l>They eate the Fatte, and ſkin the Flocke,</l>
               <l>And liue vpon the Churches ſtocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>An idle ſigne, a Shepherds Crooke</l>
               <l>In hand they beare, <note n="d" place="margin">Their Paſtoral ſtaffe, made in faſhion of a Shepheards crooke.</note> but can not brooke</l>
               <l>To preach the word (a Paſtors grace)</l>
               <l>That duty fittes not their high place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The key of knowledge they withdraw, <note n="e" place="margin">Luke 11.52.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And from Gods people ſteale <note n="f" place="margin">Ieremy, 23.30.</note> Gods Law,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">They teach traditions to be equally reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced as the Scriptures, Con. Trid. ſeſ. 4. dec. 1.</note> And mens deuies on them thruſt,</l>
               <l>Making them vnto Fancies truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:11"/>
               <l>Theſe are Romes Paſtors: wofull ſhéepe,</l>
               <l>Which left are to the Wolues to kéepe.</l>
               <l>Thou Shepheard great, &amp; Byſhop chiefe, <note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25. &amp; 5.4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Come quickly <note n="i" place="margin">Reuel. 22.20.</note> quell this Romiſh thiefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Viſible.</head>
               <l>THou tell'ſt a tale incredible,</l>
               <l>How that Gods Church is viſible:</l>
               <l>And by the Byſhops Catalogue,</l>
               <l>Wouldſt prooue thy Romiſh Synagogue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The errors here together lap't,</l>
               <l>By which the ſimple are entrap't,</l>
               <l>All which your fained Church doth hold,</l>
               <l>I meane in order to vnfold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Catholike Church defin'd aright,</l>
               <l>Cannot be ſubiect to our ſight:</l>
               <l>It is th' Elected Company, <note n="k" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And Chriſt his choſen Family. <note n="l" place="margin">Ephe. 3.15.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of this, one part in heauen liues, <note n="m" place="margin">Called the Church Triumphant.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The other here with Sathan ſtriues, <note n="n" place="margin">Termed the Church Militant.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The part aboue (youle not deny)</l>
               <l>With mortall eyes none can deſcry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſame is true of that below,</l>
               <l>It is vnſéene by vs alſo:</l>
               <l>How with mine eyes I might diſcerne,</l>
               <l>And ſée th' Elect, faine would I learne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vpon their perſons we may looke,</l>
               <l>Whoſe names are written in Gods booke, <note n="o" place="margin">The Booke of life, Phil. 4.3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>But as for their ſpirituall Being,</l>
               <l>It is a thing doth paſſe our ſéeing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Partes of Chriſts church, you Papiſts make</l>
               <l>Euen thoſe whom God will quite forſake: <note n="p" place="margin">So doeth Belarmine, lib. 3. de Eccl. Cap. 7. &amp; the Rhemiſts in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations vpon Io. 15.1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which if the matter well be ſcand,</l>
               <l>Cannot with any Scripture ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:12"/>
               <l>Of the true Church Chriſt is the Head, <note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 1.22.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In him can be no members dead, <note n="r" place="margin">They are called liuing ſtones, 1. Pet. 2.5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>His Church a Garden <note n="s" place="margin">Cant. 4.12.</note> cloſed well,</l>
               <l>In which no Reprobates can dwell: <note n="t" place="margin">So Auguſt. applyeth the place, contra Creſ. Gram. lib. 2. and Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the great, who was a Biſhop of Rome, in his Commentary vpon that place.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that, if fitly we will ſpeake,</l>
               <l>The ground you lay is very weake:</l>
               <l>In calling it a Marke moſt cléere,</l>
               <l>That Gods true Church muſt ſtill appéere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of Churches nam'd in ſeuerall,</l>
               <l>In Cities, or els Nationall,</l>
               <l>We yeeld ſometime they may be ſéene,</l>
               <l>Though ſometime they are darkened cleane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sometime the Moone with chéerefull light</l>
               <l>Shines in the height of Heauen bright: <note n="u" place="margin">Aug. vſeth that Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude in Pſalm. 9. and Epiſt. 48. and Ambroſe Hex. 4. C. 8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Sometime with Cloudes tis ouerſpred,</l>
               <l>And in the Wane cleane vaniſhed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So is the Church in ſafety ſtill,</l>
               <l>Although not alway viſible:</l>
               <l>Sometimes it ſittes in glory great,</l>
               <l>Sometime it hath no certaine Seat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Woman, which to Deſert fled,</l>
               <l>From Sathans rage to hide her head, <note n="w" place="margin">Apoc. 12.6.</note>
               </l>
               <l>By all the Learneds full conſent,</l>
               <l>The Church on earth doth repreſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The famous Church of Iſrael,</l>
               <l>Where God did promiſe ſtill to dwell, <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Was drownd ſo in Idolatry,</l>
               <l>And ſuperſtitious ſlauery,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That all true worſhip being gone,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> thought himſelfe alone: <note n="y" place="margin">1. King. 19.10.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And when Chriſt comes to iudge vs all,</l>
               <l>Then Fayth on earth ſhalbe but ſmall. <note n="z" place="margin">Luke 18.8.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How is the Church a City then, <note n="a" place="margin">Math. 5.14.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Raiſ'd on a Mount, and ſéene of men,</l>
               <l>And how a light ſet vp on hye,</l>
               <l>That all that will may it eſpye?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:12"/>
               <l>How ſhall we to the Church complaine, <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 18.17.</note>
               </l>
               <l>If of the Church no ſhew remaine?</l>
               <l>This is thy Popiſh reaſoning,</l>
               <l>And Scriptures playne miſconſtruing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt doth the Apoſtles counſell giue,<note place="margin">The true meaning of thoſe places.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Soundly to preach, and well to liue:</l>
               <l>Becauſe their places were in ſight,</l>
               <l>And 'twas their Office to giue light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They erring, many might miſſe-lead,</l>
               <l>Which in their ſteps might hap to tread:</l>
               <l>If that their Doctrine were vnſound,</l>
               <l>In falſehood many might bee drownd:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It was in vaine for them to wéene,</l>
               <l>In doing yll not to be ſéene:</l>
               <l>You are (ſayth Chriſt) vpon a Mount,</l>
               <l>To be well markt, make full account. <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thus Chry. and The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilact expound this place,</hi> Paideuſi antous enagonious einai, cai acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beis peri ton bion, os para panton blepeſthe mellontas.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſheweth wherein our duety ſtands,</l>
               <l>And what God lookes for at our hands:</l>
               <l>Who call'd are to the Miniſtry,</l>
               <l>To labour in Gods Huſbandry. <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But from hence how may prooued bée</l>
               <l>The Churches viſibility?</l>
               <l>This place affoords a ſlender proofe,</l>
               <l>And litle for the Popes behoofe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet you perhaps will vrge it ſtill,</l>
               <l>The Paſtors are ſet on a Hyll,</l>
               <l>And called Light: euen ſo ſay I,</l>
               <l>But all men can them not deſcry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For thoſe which want ſpirituall eyes, <note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 1.18.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nor are by ſearching <note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 5.39.</note> Scriptures wiſe, <note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 5.15, 17.</note>
               </l>
               <l>This mounted City can not ſée,</l>
               <l>Nor where theſe lightſome Paſtors bée. <note n="h" place="margin">This was the anſwere of Aug. to the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts. Tract. 1. in Ep. Iohan.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt bids vs we the Church ſhould tell,</l>
               <l>If things be not reformed well.</l>
               <l>By Church, hee meanes all ſuch as bée</l>
               <l>Indued with Authority. <note n="i" place="margin">The ſame which Paul calleth <hi>Preſbyterion,</hi> 1. Tim. 4.14. The Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:13"/>
               <l>Theſe Office-bearers all men ſée,</l>
               <l>In times of ſetled Souerainty,</l>
               <l>Yea, and among them ſelues th'are knowne,</l>
               <l>When th' outward ſtate is ouerthrowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Error of this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Argument.</note>When that was ſaid in ſpeciall,</l>
               <l>You turne to Church in generall.</l>
               <l>Thereby you may deceiue ſome fooles:</l>
               <l>But ſoone it will be ſéene in Schooles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Argument of outward ſtate,</l>
               <l>Which for a Marke you intimate,</l>
               <l>Againſt that thing doth ſtrongly make,</l>
               <l>Which you to prooue do vndertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Romes ſtate hath ſometimes bin obſcur'd,</l>
               <l>And hath diſgraces ſoule endur'd:</l>
               <l>Burnt,<note n="k" place="margin">By the Gothes, 547.</note> ſackt, <note n="l" place="margin">By Charles, Duke of Burbon, in the dayes of Pope Clement the 7. wherevpon was made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clauſe in the Letany, <hi>Sancta Maria, &amp;c.</hi> O ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mary, pray for Pope Clement, &amp;c.</note> ſome Popes impriſoned,<note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 14. Boniface 8. about the yeere 1304.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Some glad to fly, <note n="n" place="margin">Iohn 17. fled to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truria.</note> ſome baniſhed. <note n="o" place="margin">Vigilius 18. &amp; Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory 9. about the yeere 1227.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where did your glorious Church abide,</l>
               <l>When Popes were glad themſelues to hide?</l>
               <l>Peace, peace, no more of this for ſhame:</l>
               <l>Rome ſayth thou wilt her cleane defame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Succeſsion.</note>Succeſſion cometh next in place,</l>
               <l>Whereby thou ſéekſt thy Church to grace:</l>
               <l>Your turne Succeſſion cannot ſerue,</l>
               <l>If from the Trueth Succeſſion ſwerue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Iewiſh Church from Aaron,</l>
               <l>A iuſt deſcent might ſtand vpon:</l>
               <l>Euen when they crucifide our Lord,</l>
               <l>And hated all that lou'd his Word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If we ſhall ſay, that Church was true,</l>
               <l>Conſiſting of ſo vile a crue,</l>
               <l>We caſt Chriſt and the Apoſtles out,</l>
               <l>Among the baſe and damned rout.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Grecian Churches at this day,</l>
               <l>For their defence as much can ſay: <note n="p" place="margin">At Conſtantinople there hath beene a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Succeſsion from S. Andrew, Niceph. At Alexandria, from Saint Marke.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Yet you of them doe giue this doome,</l>
               <l>That in Gods church they haue no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:13"/>
               <l>Yet if Succeſſion were a ſigne,</l>
               <l>Which your graund captayne Bellarmine</l>
               <l>Dares not auouch, <note n="q" place="margin">Bellarmine ſayeth, it followeth negatiuely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where there is no ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there is no church: but not affirmatiuely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where there is ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is a Church.</note> I ſayne would ſée,</l>
               <l>How Rome can proue her Pedigrée.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You call your Church Saint Peters chayre,</l>
               <l>As though the Pope were Peters Heyre;</l>
               <l>But if that ground we once deny,</l>
               <l>What Papiſt can it verify?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You cannot proue by holy Writ,</l>
               <l>Peter at Rome did Biſhop ſit:</l>
               <l>The onely place which you doe name, <note n="r" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.13. The Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts ſay, that there, by Babylon is ment Rome, &amp; ſo they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe Rome to be Babylon.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Returneth to your greater ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The things you fetch from Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>Touching this poynt, doe not agrée, <note n="s" place="margin">Oſorius ſayth, Peter came to Rome in the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning of Claudius raigne; Hierome, in the 2. yere: others, in the 4. yere: other, the 13, yere. Damaſus ſaith, he came thither in Neroes raign; ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no certainty in that which they make an vndoubted principle</note>
               </l>
               <l>And what our part hath herein ſed,</l>
               <l>By Papiſts ſtands vnanſwered.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if hee Biſhop were indéede,</l>
               <l>Tell me who next did him ſuccéede?</l>
               <l>Some, Clement, <note n="t" place="margin">The Popes decrees hold ſo.</note> and ſome, Linus hold. <note n="v" place="margin">Dorotheus, Euſeb. li. 3. cap. 4. Hieron in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talo.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thus your ſucceſſion is controld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once was a Pope ſuppoſ'd a man, <note n="w" place="margin">Iohn 8. Platina: The womans name was Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berta, a Dutch woman of Maguntium.</note>
               </l>
               <l>But prou'd in time a Courtezan.</l>
               <l>Then eyther your Succeſſion ſhranke,</l>
               <l>Or you muſt put her in the ranke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Popes there were ſome two <note n="x" place="margin">Two Popes together Anno 1083. &amp; Anno 1058. &amp; 1062.</note> or thrée, <note n="y" place="margin">Bened. 9. Silueſt. 3. Greg. 6. all at one time: and at another time, Ben. 13. a Spaniſh Pope, Greg. 12. a French Pope, and Iohn 23. an Italian Pope.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Where the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might your ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be?</l>
               <l>One Schiſme held almoſt fourty yere, <note n="z" place="margin">39. yeeres.</note>
               </l>
               <l>From Pope to Pope, as doeth appeare. <note n="a" place="margin">Let their Anceſtors ſpeake.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One Councel <note n="b" place="margin">The Councill of Conſtance.</note> did theſe Popes put downe,</l>
               <l>And to another gaue the crowne.</l>
               <l>When theſe falſe Popes the place poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>I thinke youle ſay Succeſſion ceaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:14"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Vnity.</head>
               <l>'TIs true, Chriſts Church is alwayes one,</l>
               <l>Tyd vnto him as Head alone:</l>
               <l>The partes thereof do well agrée, <note n="c" place="bottom">Acts 4.23.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Like children of one Family.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet not euery company,</l>
               <l>Together linckt in Vnity,</l>
               <l>Muſt by and by be called good.</l>
               <l>If Trueth by them ſhalbe withſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To make a Calfe they all agréed, <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 32.1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>All cry'd, <hi>Let Chriſt be crucifi'd:</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Math. 27.22.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great is Diana,</hi> with a ſhoute</l>
               <l>At once the people all cry'd out. <note n="f" place="margin">Acts 19.34.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Iohn ſayd, they ſhould yéeld to the Beaſt.</l>
               <l>Euen from the greateſt to the leaſt: <note n="g" place="margin">Apoc. 13.16.</note>
               </l>
               <l>As Chriſt his City is but one,</l>
               <l>So is the Deuils Babylon. <note n="h" place="margin">Vt eſt dei vna eccleſia, ſic eſt diaboli vn a Babylon, <hi>Aug.</hi> de Ciui. Dei.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The beſt ſometimes do diſagrée, <note n="i" place="margin">Peter and Paul, Gal, 2.11. Paul &amp; Barnabas, Acts 15.39. Chryſoſt. Theophilact, and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, Auguſtine and Hierome, Cyrill &amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Each man hath his Infirmity:</l>
               <l>Better the Diſcord bringing Light,</l>
               <l>Then is agréement without right. <note n="k" place="margin">Kreiſſon empathous om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onoias he vper euſebeias diaſtaſis, <hi>Nazianz:</hi> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione prima de pace.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet by this Marke, if Rome be try'd,</l>
               <l>It will fall hard vpon your ſide:</l>
               <l>Your ioynt-conſent we can not find,</l>
               <l>Nor that you all are of one mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If we ſhall credit Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>You can not bragge of Vnity:</l>
               <l>Where twenty ſeueral ſchiſmes haue béen, <note n="l" place="margin">Genebrardus in Chro.</note>
               </l>
               <l>What Harmony may there be ſéene?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lawes which one determineth,</l>
               <l>The Pope that follows cancelleth: <note n="m" place="margin">Stephen 6. abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all his Predeceſſors decrees. Formoſus tooke vp his body, cut two fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d off, and buried him agayne.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Yet things by him aboliſhed,</l>
               <l>By next Popes are eſtabliſhed. <note n="n" place="margin">The following Popes Theodorus 2. Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Ioh. 10. confirmed all Formoſus his actes.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:14"/>
               <l>And yet another <note n="o" place="margin">After all, Pope Sergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us diſanulled their acts, tooke vp Formoſus his body, &amp; caſt it into Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bur, Ex. Poly. Chron.</note> comes behind,</l>
               <l>Who with the former fault doth find,</l>
               <l>And all which they did quite diſplace,</l>
               <l>Reduceth to the former grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus one ſage Counſell doth decrée,</l>
               <l>Another ſayth it may not bée: <note n="p" place="margin">The firſt Nicene Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell allowed Prieſts ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in both kinds. The Councels of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; Baſil forbade the Laity y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the cup. The cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent forbiddeth both the Cup to the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and marriage to the Clergy. The third Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Carthage pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced him accurſed, &amp; called him the Forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Antichriſt, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhould terme himſelfe Vniuerſal Biſhop; but now the Councel of Trent curſeth him, who ſhall deny the Pope of Rome to bee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the world. The general councel of Conſtantinople ouerthrewe Images. The ſecond Nicene councell decreed them to bee worſhipped. Againe, the Councell of Franckfort, vnder Charles the great, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it to be Idolatry, &amp; accurſeth the Nicene councel. Many the like differences might eaſily be alledged.</note>
               </l>
               <l>That which one Sect <note n="q" place="margin">In anno 1476. there was a great controuerſy betwixt the Franciſcanes &amp; Dominicanes, touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin Mary, whether ſhe were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued in ſin or not. The Do, held ſhe was, the Fra. the contrary: but the Pope ioyning with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fr. 4. of the other were conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned &amp; burned at Berne.</note> or Author <note n="r" place="margin">Alph. de Caſtro li. 1. c. 6. holds the Pope inferior to the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel. The opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites at this day, is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is aboue the Councel. About the Euchariſt they haue a world of differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues; as whether Chriſt did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bleſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; wine: or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid, This is my body, whether ſo much bread as is taken onely, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated: whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the bread be turned to nothing, or cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chr. whether there be a bodily motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Sacra. whether the body of Chr. in the Sacr. can be touched: how the accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in the Sacr. are with out a ſubiect: whether they ſtick in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire, or in the body of Chr. or in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubiect: whether the accidents can be broken: whether they can nouriſh: whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water mingled with the wine, be turned into Chriſts blood. Whence come wormes in the Hoſte.</note> likes,</l>
               <l>The ſame another cleane out ſtrikes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know, you Papiſts do agrée,</l>
               <l>To worke the Churches miſery:</l>
               <l>So Herode was made <note n="s" place="margin">Luke 23.12.</note> Pilates frend,</l>
               <l>To bring our Sauiour to his end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some yéeld, as fearing to reſiſt:</l>
               <l>(Such is the power of Antichriſt:)</l>
               <l>You may not call this Vnity,</l>
               <l>But rather bloudy Tyranny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:15"/>
               <l>Some ioyne, becauſe they do not ſée</l>
               <l>The very depth of Poperie:</l>
               <l>To build vpon the Church beliefe,</l>
               <l>Of lay-Religion is the Briefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some for eaſe and bellies ſake,</l>
               <l>Do to your Church them ſelues betake:</l>
               <l>As Monkes, and ſuch as Loytryng loue,</l>
               <l>Whom none but Romiſts can approoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is your Romiſh Concordance,</l>
               <l>Among your ſelues at variance:</l>
               <l>Though all for ſome reſpects are led,</l>
               <l>To méete together in one Head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In one point more, I néedes muſt ſtay,</l>
               <l>Though nam'd of you but by the way:</l>
               <l>Leſt with a Phraſe of Peters Keyes,</l>
               <l>You dazell ſhould the peoples eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By Keyes, is meant the power to preach,</l>
               <l>And in Gods Truth the Church to teach: <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 11.52.</note>
               </l>
               <l>By it <note n="u" place="margin">Viz. Preaching.</note> Heauen's opened to receiue</l>
               <l>All thoſe which truely do belieue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is the power to looſe and tye,</l>
               <l>Which Chriſt gaue to the Miniſtry, <note n="w" place="margin">Therefore Miniſters are ſayd both to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miniſtery of Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, 2. Cor. 5.18. and the Miniſtery of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, 2. Cor. 10.6.</note>
               </l>
               <l>It was intended vnto all, <note n="x" place="margin">Our Lord, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of one, gaue the keyes to all, to ſhew the Vnity of all, Cyp. de ſimp. praelatorum: and Leo, a Biſhop of Rome is of the ſame iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, In Sermone de Natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Though ſpoke to one in ſeuerall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When to beleeuers we giue Hope,</l>
               <l>Then is the Gate of Heauen ſet ope:</l>
               <l>When Mercies promiſe is repeal'd,</l>
               <l>Then by the Keyes that Gate is ſeal'd. <note n="y" place="margin">To bind and looſe, is no other thing, but to declare Gods ſentence, Hieron. in Mat. 16.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Peter did his Fayth confeſſe,</l>
               <l>Th' Apoſtles by dyd meane no leſſe: <note n="z" place="margin">Auſtine ſayth, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered for all, Hom. in Ioh. 124. and elſewhere often: <hi>Vnus pro multis reſpondit:</hi> one made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for all: and Lyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>Confeſsio Petri, erat confeſſio alienorum.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>And that which Chriſt to Peter ſpake,</l>
               <l>We may not from the other take. <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cuncti claues Regni,</hi> &amp;c. All receyue the keyes of heauen, Hier. lib. 1. aduerſus Ioui.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Each true and faythfull Miniſter,</l>
               <l>Is Peters rightfull Succeſſer:</l>
               <l>Then ſpeake no more of Peters Keyes,</l>
               <l>Except th' art ſworne the Pope to pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:15"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Holy.<note place="margin">Why the Church is called Holy.</note>
               </head>
               <l>THou ſayſt, the Church we holy call.</l>
               <l>And ſo we do acknowledge all:</l>
               <l>What in the Créede our mouthes confeſſe,</l>
               <l>Our heartes within beléeue no leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Purity decayed before, <note n="b" place="margin">By Adams fall.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto his Church Chriſt doth reſtore.</l>
               <l>That which is here in leſſe degrée,</l>
               <l>The ſame in heauen ſhall perfit bée.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou knewſt Romes Impurity,</l>
               <l>Thou wouldſt bragge of Sanctity:</l>
               <l>A ſincke of ſinne, a Sea of Euill,</l>
               <l>A place poſſeſſed of the Deuill. <note n="c" place="margin">Gallus Senonenſis wrote aboue 400 yeres ago, that Sathan was let looſe at Rome, to deſtroy the church. Th. Becket, a Romiſh ſaint, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe to be true, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no right at Rome. The B. of Worceſter, a Papiſt, told Philpot, that he thoght, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes he ſaw in Rome made him an Heretike.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your Popes beare names of Holynes,</l>
               <l>But none more full of Wickednes:</l>
               <l>Let Storyes ſpeake, enquire of them,</l>
               <l>What Popes haue worne the Diademe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some Heretikes, <note n="d" place="margin">Marcellinus Pope, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to the Idols of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Painims: Platin. &amp; Vola ter. Liberius Pope, an Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Plat. &amp; Hiero. in Catal. ſcrip. Eccl. &amp; in Chro. Anaſt. 2. Pope, an Acatian. Plat. Vigil. an Eutchyan. Liber in breuiario. Honorius, a Monothelite, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by the Romane Councell, vnder Adrian 2.</note> ſome Murtherers, <note n="e" place="margin">Pope Alexander 6. poyſoned Gemes the great Turkes brother, committed to his cuſtody, Hiero. Marius, Munſt. lib. 4. Coſm. Pope Hildebrand hired one to kill the Emperor, Benno Cardinalis.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Inceſtuous ſome, <note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 13. Pope, committed inceſt with his two ſiſters: Luith. prand. lib. <hi>6.</hi> Hee was wounded in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultry, Platina. Alexander <hi>6.</hi> lay with his owne daughter. Vol.</note> ſome Sorcerers: <note n="g" place="margin">Hildebrand: ſo ſayth Benno the Card. Pope Silueſter 2. gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Deuill, to bee Pope. Pla. Ioannes ſtella: many other were Magicians, as Iohn 21. Benedict. 9. &amp;c.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Some noted for their Cruelty, <note n="h" place="margin">Pope Alexander 6. cut off the hands &amp; feet of one Mancinellus, becauſe he wrote againſt his filthineſſe. Iohn 13. cut off the hands and noſes of diuers Cardinals. Plat.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Some for their monſtrous Blaſphemy. <note n="i" place="margin">Pope Hildebrand threw the ſacrament into the fire. Benno Card. Io. 22. derided y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, held y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules to be mortal, &amp; was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Councel of Conſtance, 1. 2. ſeſ. 11. called a Deuil incarnat. Leo 10. writing to Cardinall Bembus, calleth the ſtory of Chriſt, a fable. Io. 13. called the deuil to help him at dice, &amp; dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k to him, Luith. p. lib. 6</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:16"/>
               <l>One Pope <note n="k" place="margin">Pope Sergius 3.</note> a famous Leuimen <note n="l" place="margin">Marozia, wife to Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</note> kept,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Baſtard to the Popedome crept: <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 11. or as ſome count, Io. 12. See Plat. and Luithprand.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Another graunted Liberty,</l>
               <l>To practiſe beaſtly Sodomy. <note n="n" place="margin">Sixtus 4. granted li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Cardinall of Saint Lucy in the three hote moneths, Iune, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Auguſt, to vſe Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitry. Weſellus Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningenſis in a Treatiſe <hi>de Indulg. Papalibus,</hi> at the foote of the licence, was written, <hi>Fiat vt peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> Be it as it is requeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who but the Pope receiueth rent,</l>
               <l>Which from the Stewes to him is ſent? <note n="o" place="margin">Euery commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harlot in Rome payd a Fee to Pope Sixtus 4. Agrippa in his declam. ad Loua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Let Rome and Venice make report,</l>
               <l>And all that thither doe reſort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who hath in Méeter vile expreſt</l>
               <l>The ſinne, which nature doeth deteſt?</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Beneuentum</hi> name the man: <note n="p" place="margin">The Archbiſhop of Beneuentum, Iohannes a Caſa, Deane of the Popes chamber, vſed Sodomy, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it in Italian Meeter: the booke was printed at Venice, by Troianus Nauus: ſee the writing of Paulus Vergerius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Archbiſhop.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Doe thou diſproue it, if thou can.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If this among your Heads be found,</l>
               <l>How ſhall we thinke the members ſound?</l>
               <l>Lord, bleſſe vs from ſuch holy Popes,</l>
               <l>And, Lord, make voyd all popiſh hopes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like to your Popes, your ſeruice is,<note place="margin">Holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Wanting no ſtore of blaſphemies:</l>
               <l>Which, leſt the people ſhould eſpy,</l>
               <l>You hyde in Latine ſecrecy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I néede no better witneſſes,</l>
               <l>Then your allowed Porteſſes,</l>
               <l>Your Miſſals and your Letanies,</l>
               <l>And all your forged Pſalteries.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What we to God alone muſt giue,</l>
               <l>That to the Saints you doe deriue.</l>
               <l>God will not from his glory part, <note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 48.11.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Yet you to creatures it conuert.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto the Saints you prayers make, <note n="r" place="margin">There is neither commaundement in the Scripture, that we ſhould pray to ſaints, nor promiſe, that if we doe pray to them, we ſhall be heard; vpon which 2. euery lawful praier muſt be built.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And beg ſaluation for their ſake: <note n="s" place="margin">In their praiers vpon the ſaints dayes, ſtil thoſe words come in, that by their merits we may haue profit, by their requeſts wee may be deliuered &amp;c. And Lambard ſaith, the Saints do <hi>iunare nos merito,</hi> l. 4. diſt. 45. d. 10.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19654:16"/>You do adore a piece of bread, <note n="t" place="margin">When it is carried in proceſſion; for though it were true, that the bread in the Sacrament is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the Body of Chriſt, yet the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being ended, it muſt needs return to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer nature.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And make fond <note n="u" place="margin">They are fond, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe touching th' eſtate of the dead, there is no certainty.</note> prayers for the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You knéele downe to a Croſſe of wood, <note n="w" place="margin">All hayle, O Croſſe, our only hope, &amp;c. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe righteouſneſſe to the godly, and giue pardon to the guilty. <hi>In breniario infra,</hi> Heb. 4. Quad.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thinking thereby to purchaſe good:</l>
               <l>And for ſome things you would haue done,</l>
               <l>You pray the Virgin, charge her Sonne. <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Roga Patrem, iube natu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; iure matris impera, &amp;c.</hi> Pray the father, charge thy ſonne, commaund by the right of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>In officio beata Maria.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With Chriſt you do ſaint Frances ioyne, <note n="y" place="margin">They ſay, that Saint Francis could ſaue all that ſhall liue after him to the end of the world, through his merits, from euerlaſting Death. Floſc. beati Franciſ. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formit. ſ. Fran. Tho. lib. 4. diſt. 4. art. 3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſo his glory doe purloyne:</l>
               <l>One Mediator <note n="z" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5. That place proueth, that there is but one Mediator, as well as that there is but one God.</note> we doe know,</l>
               <l>You haue ioynd with him many moe. <note n="a" place="margin">The forme of Abſolution to Penitentiaries runneth thus: The paſsion of Chriſt, and the merites of the bleſſed Virgin, of Saint Peter and Saint Paul, and of other hee and ſhee Saints, be vnto thee in remiſsion of ſinnes.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We doe the Virgin Bleſſed call, <note n="b" place="margin">Luke 1.48.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſay ſhee paſſed women all:</l>
               <l>But when you call her, Gate of Grace, <note n="c" place="margin">Coeli ſeneſtra: Regis al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i ian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, &amp;c.</note>
               </l>
               <l>We ſay, Chriſts honour you deface.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The thing which made her ſpirit glad,</l>
               <l>Was, that ſhée ſuch a Sauiour had: <note n="d" place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Can ſhe on him commaundement haue,</l>
               <l>Whoſe helpe ſhée néeded her to ſaue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">What honour is due to the Saints.</note>This honour to the Saints we giue,</l>
               <l>We craue Gods grace like them to liue, <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>We care to keepe their memory, <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And God in them we glorify. <note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 1.23.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">Holy Ceremonies.</note>Your Ceremonies idle be,</l>
               <l>And ſauour moſt of vanity:</l>
               <l>You ſtand ſo much on out ward ſhow,</l>
               <l>That you the ſubſtance ouerthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:17"/>
               <l>With Images and Pictures gay,</l>
               <l>You ſteale the peoples hearts away:</l>
               <l>Well may you pleaſe the outward eye,</l>
               <l>The Spirit you do not edifie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A pretie play, to ſée a Prieſt</l>
               <l>Toſſing his God betwéene his fiſt:</l>
               <l>Such Geſtures, and ſuch Apiſh mowes,</l>
               <l>Such warbling, and ſuch Anticke ſhowes: <note n="h" place="margin">Whoſo readeth the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Maſſe, ſhall there ſee a world of idle &amp; ridiculus ceremonies.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now bends, now ducks, now ſtands vpright,</l>
               <l>Then turnes him to the peoples ſight:</l>
               <l>Now ſighes, now twenty croſſes makes,</l>
               <l>And 'ore his head the Wafer ſhakes:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then waſheth, then the Challice lickes,</l>
               <l>And ſhuttes his Idoll in the Pixe:</l>
               <l>But ſtill the man is much afeard,</l>
               <l>Leſt ought ſhould hang vpon his beard.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Meane while, the vulgar in a maze,</l>
               <l>Vpon the Caky Idol gaze,</l>
               <l>And knock and kneele, &amp; thinke them well,</l>
               <l>That they haue heard the ſacring Bell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell mée, I pray thée, doth God will,</l>
               <l>With ſuch fond Kites his Church to fill.</l>
               <l>They neuer came into his thought: <note n="i" place="margin">Iere. 19.5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Tradition onely hath them brought. <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <p>They ſay indeed, that they haue the forme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe, by the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtles. Rhem. 1. Cor. 11. ſ. 22. but the truth is, that it was now a piece and then a piece, patched vp by their own Popes, Sixtùs 2. broght in the Sanctus: Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius 1. the Pax. Leo 1. added this clauſe (A ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacrifice and vnblou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Hoſt:) Gelacius, the Prefaces, Collects, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dualts. Symmachus, the Gloria in excelſis. Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus 1. the Proceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Pelagius 2. nyne Prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before the Canon. Sergius 1. Agnus Dei: and Gregory 1. confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that one Scolaſticus made moſt part of the Canon.</p>
                     <p>Holy maſſe or ſacrifice.</p>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your Rites and Maſſe do well agrée,</l>
               <l>Both full of groſſe Idolatry:</l>
               <l>Both are vnholy and vnſound,</l>
               <l>Both wantyng holy Scripture ground,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You ſay that in the Euchariſt,</l>
               <l>To God is offred by the Prieſt,</l>
               <l>A Sacrifice in wine and bread, <note n="l" place="margin">Rhem. Heb. 7. ſ. 8. Concil. Trident. ſeſ. 22. cap. 1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Both for the liuing and the dead. <note n="m" place="margin">Conc. Trid. ſeſ. 22. cap. 3.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke firſt what Chriſt did inſtitute, <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 26.26. Mat. 14.22. Lu. 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.24.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And that one place ſhall you refute:</l>
               <l>What he did, we muſt do likewiſe, <note n="o" place="margin">This do ye, 1. Cor. 11.25.</note>
               </l>
               <l>There's no word of a Sacrifice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:17"/>
               <l>By this (ſayd Chriſt) <hi>Remember me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſhewes he would not preſent <note n="p" place="margin">Bodily.</note> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>We keepe ſuch things in memory,</l>
               <l>Which we behold not really.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Prieſts of old did euery day</l>
               <l>Some Offring on the Altar lay. <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 10.11.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Chriſts holy Offring is but One,</l>
               <l>Performed by himſelfe alone. <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 10.12.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If Chriſt ſhall often offred bée,</l>
               <l>We ſhall his ſuffrings multiply:</l>
               <l>As on the Croſſe he dyed not twice.</l>
               <l>So there's no ſecond Sacrifice: <note n="s" place="margin">Heb. 9.25, 26, 27, 28.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There's now no ſacrificing Prieſt:</l>
               <l>That Office reſteth vpon Chriſt: <note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 7.23, 24.</note>
               </l>
               <l>It comes to none ſucceſſiuely:</l>
               <l>'Tis his for all eternity. <note n="u" place="margin">The office of a Prieſt, ſo far forth as we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therby a Sacrificer, whom the Grecians call <hi>iereus,</hi> belongs onely to Chriſt, and cannot paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to any other, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the name of Prieſt in that ſence: but as the name of Prieſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Greeke word <hi>Preſbyteros,</hi> which ſignifieth an Elder, it can not ſimply be miſliked.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can a Maſſe a Pardon bring,</l>
               <l>Sith 'tis a bloud-leſſe Offering? <note n="w" place="margin">Heb. 9.22.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Chriſt hath procur'd Remiſſion: <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 9.12.</note>
               </l>
               <l>What needs a new Oblation? <note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 10.18.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sée then your holy Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>A thing without all warantize</l>
               <l>Of Scriptures, or of Writers ſage,</l>
               <l>Which liued in the pureſt Age. <note n="z" place="margin">The Maſſe, as it is now, was not in vſe in the Church, 1200. yeres after Chriſt: It neuer came to the full perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (though it was in hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching before) vntill the Councel of Lateran, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Inno. 3.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Holy Sacraments.</note>The Sacraments in number twayne,</l>
               <l>You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ek'd haue with a longer trayne,</l>
               <l>The ſeuen-headed Romiſh Beaſt, <note n="a" place="margin">Reuelation 17.8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Two to ſeuen hath encreaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Both Baptiſme, <note n="b" place="margin">Mathew 28.19.</note> and that holy Feaſt <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.24. &amp;c.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Commaunded are by Chriſtes beheaſt:</l>
               <l>Shew mée but one commaundement,</l>
               <l>To prooue an other Sacrament. <note n="d" place="margin">No Father within an hundred yeeres after Chriſt, acknowledged ſeuen Sacraments of the newe Teſtament: And Auguſtine ſaith, the Sacraments are, <hi>numero pauciſſima,</hi> feweſt in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Ep. 118. now two is the leaſt number.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19654:18"/>Two in the Old, <note n="e" place="margin">Viz. Ordinary.</note> two in the New:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Viz. The forme of Gods worſhip vnder the law.</note>So ſhall we haue proportion true:</l>
               <l>Name what in th' ancient Liturgy,</l>
               <l>Your fiue falſe Symboles do ſupply. <note n="g" place="margin">The Sacraments of the new Teſtament, ſucceed the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the old: if then they can name no Sacraments of the olde Teſtament, in the place whereof their fiue ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhould come, then they cannot iuſtify them to be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe Sacraments which holy bée,</l>
               <l>You ſtayn'd haue with your Pedlery:</l>
               <l>In Baptiſme, oyle, lights, ſpittle, creame,</l>
               <l>Your Exorciſme, and coniur'd ſtreame;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Were theſe inuented by Gods Spirit,</l>
               <l>Or found you them in Holy Writ?</l>
               <l>Whence had you all that rituous ſtore</l>
               <l>Vſ'd in the Maſſe and nam'd before?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">Holy dayes.</note>You ſpeake next of Feſtiuities,</l>
               <l>And Holy day Solemnities:</l>
               <l>Thou thinkſt by this, with eaſines</l>
               <l>To prooue thy Churches Holines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Trueth is, mens Conſcience you enthrall. <note n="h" place="margin">Bellarmine ſaith, men are bound in conſcience to keepe the Feſtiuities of the Church, lib. 3. ca. 10. prop. 3. and ſo doe the Rhemiſts, Gal. 4. ſ. 5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To many an idle Feſtiuall: <note n="i" place="margin">Very neere 200. if wee put thoſe together which were determined of, <hi>Concil. Oxon. ſub Steph.</hi> &amp; which we read in the marginall Notes vpon the Rhemiſts Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Youle haue them be as ſtrictly kept,</l>
               <l>As Gods owne day by his precept.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of Feaſtes ſome lowe, ſome higher bée,</l>
               <l>Some great, ſome leſſer in degrée:</l>
               <l>Some double more, ſome double leſſe:</l>
               <l>A treble fault ſome to tranſgreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So with your doubling and redoubling ſtile,</l>
               <l>The ſimple people you beguile:</l>
               <l>The Lord is weary of your Feaſts, <note n="k" place="margin">Iſay 1.14.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And likes not your deuiſed reſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All dayes are like in Holines,</l>
               <l>None holy more, none holy leſſe: <note n="l" place="margin">The difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt dayes, is in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation &amp; vſe, and not in the nature of the day: if one day had bene in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture holyer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, the Sabboth might not haue bene altered.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Paul thought his labour was in vayne,</l>
               <l>Where dayes diſtinctions did remaine. <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 4.10, 11.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou hoy'ſt to put vs in ſome feare,</l>
               <l>With ſpeaking of the Kalendere: <note n="n" place="margin">Saints canonized.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thou aſk'ſt what Fayth all thoſe did hold,</l>
               <l>Whoſe names are found therein enrold?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:18"/>
               <l>I tell thée plaine, 'tis nought to me,</l>
               <l>What many a one there nam'd might bée:</l>
               <l>My Fayth's not ſo ſet on the Racke,</l>
               <l>To ſéeke ſtrength from the Almanacke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſure I am, what we profeſſe,</l>
               <l>Some that are there, beleeued no leſſe: <note n="o" place="margin">As Peter, Paul, Mary &amp;c. and ſome there na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which ſuffered per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in the ten firſt perſecutions of the Church.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Our Fayth and theirs doth well agrée,</l>
               <l>And you with them at variance bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You Churches make and Holy dayes,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Saints, and Martyrs praiſe:</l>
               <l>But vs which do bleéeue the ſame,</l>
               <l>You ſeeke to kill and to defame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou aſk'ſt who them canonized,</l>
               <l>Whoſe names are there enregiſtred?</l>
               <l>You ſay the Pope. I aſke againe,</l>
               <l>Wilt thou that ſainting power maintaine? <note n="p" place="margin">The cuſtome of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizing Saints, was not heard, till one thouſand yeres after Chriſt, in the dayes of Alexander 3. and Gregory 7.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Can any mortall Creature tell,</l>
               <l>Who goes to Heauen, and who to Hell?</l>
               <l>All Iudgement, Paul bid vs forbeare,</l>
               <l>Vntill the Lord himſelfe appeare. <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.5.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Heauen to ſitte or high or low,</l>
               <l>Is it in mans power to beſtow? <note n="r" place="margin">Math. 20.23.</note>
               </l>
               <l>What Byſhop can, or Saints inueſt,</l>
               <l>Or ſhutte men from eternall Reſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some one Pope doth a Saint enſtall:</l>
               <l>His graunt another doth recall: <note n="s" place="margin">Boniface 8. cauſed Hermannus Ferrarienſ, who had beene canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for a Saint 30 yeres before, to bee taken out of his graue, and burned <hi>anno,</hi> 1300.</note>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis but a ſilly dignity,</l>
               <l>That's Subiect to vncertainty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Among your Saints euen thoſe are ſéene,</l>
               <l>Which to their Prince haue traitors béen. <note n="t" place="margin">As Thomas Becket, and Elizabeth Barton, called The holy Mayd of Kent.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Though that our Church ſuch Saints deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>To it it is no preiudice.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19654:19"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Heretikes.</head>
               <l>THe Caueat touching Heretikes,</l>
               <l>Doth make againſt falſe Catholikes;</l>
               <l>We know full well, that Popery</l>
               <l>Is but a Maſſe of Hereſy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe Errors which of old were hatcht,</l>
               <l>Your Church together bath them patcht,<note n="w" place="margin">It mayntayneth free will, and merit of works with the Pelagians. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine: The Pelagians held children to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, Aug. <hi>contra Iul.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 5. So the Church of Rome ſayeth, Concupiſcence is no ſin. It holdes Imagery with the Simonians, Baſilidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Carpocratians: and with the two latter, they ſecret their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Iren. lib. 1. cap. 23. Epiph. Hereſ. 24. It al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth praying in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue with the Oſſeni, Epiph. Haere. 19. It accounteth mariage vncleane, with Tatianus, hae. 46. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth wedlock in their Prieſts; as the Manichees did in their Choſen ones, Aug. Ep. 74. With the ſame Heretikes it vſeth bread onely in the Communion, Leo ſer. 4. de Quad. and placeth faſting in the diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of meats, Aug. <hi>de Morib. Eccl. &amp; Manich.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 23. It thinks that all neceſſary doctrine is not contained in the Scripture, with Montanus, Ep. Haer. 48. It braggeth of inherent righteouſneſſe, with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thari, Iſid, Etym. lib. 8. cap. de Haer. Chriſt: It worſhippeth Angels with the Angelici, Aug. <hi>ad Quoduuli,</hi> cap. 39. It denyeth the preaching of the word to be a note of the Church, with the Donatiſts, Aug. <hi>in variis locis:</hi> and with them tyeth the Church to one ſet place, Caſſ. in Pſal. 60. It worſhippeth the Croſſe, with the Armenians, <hi>Euthymius in Panoplia.</hi> Thus in many other poynts it partaketh with the ancient Heretikes.</note>
               </l>
               <l>On them ſhe puts a fairer name,</l>
               <l>But in effect they are the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You raz'd haue the Foundation</l>
               <l>Of all Trueth and Religion:</l>
               <l>You chang'd haue the Sincerity</l>
               <l>Of all the Groundes of Piety. <note n="w" place="margin">As for example, Firſt, the Article of Iuſtification, the efficient cauſe of our Saluation and Righteouſnes by the Scripture, is Gods loue and grace onely, 2. Tim. 1, 9. Tit. 2.11. Epheſ. 1.5. Iohn 3.6. The Papiſts ſay, God is moued by our preparing works. So held Maluend in his diſputation with Bucer at Ratisbone: ſo Bonauenture lib. 1. ſen. diſt. 41. Queſt, 1. Touching the matter of our Iuſtification, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:19654:19"/>
propoundeth nothing but Chriſts obedience, Rom. 5.19. &amp; 10.4. The Papiſts place our Righteouſnes before God in our owne works &amp; merits, Con. Trid. ſ. 6. c. 7. For the Forme (as Scholers cal it) of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is by the Scriptures, the imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſts righteouſnes, 2. Cor. 5.21. The Papiſts place it in our merits, Rhemiſt 2. Tim. 4. ſ. 4. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Chriſtian Religion, that the law cannot be fulfilled by vs, &amp; that no man is to expect righteouſnes of ſaluation by it, Rom. 8.3. Acts 15.10. Gal. 2.15, 16. &amp; 3.10. The Papiſts maintayne, that men may keep y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, Con. Trid. ſ. 6. c. 11. yea, &amp; that they may perform more then the Law binds vnto: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce are ſprung the works of Supererogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Indulgences, which that Councell ſo highly prizeth. ſeſ. 21. ca. 9. A third ground of Religion ouerthrown by them, is, that eternal death is due to euery ſinne. This the Scripture auoucheth, Rom. 5.12. &amp; 6.23. Ezek. 18.14. The Papiſts teach ſome ſinnes to be in their owne nature pardonable, not deſeruing death, Con. Trid. ſeſ. 6. c. 11. From which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion aroſe Purgatory. A fourth ground of Religion, is the certainty of Saluation. That beleeuers may be certayn of Saluation, is the doctrine of the Scripture, Rom. 8.38. Heb. 11.1. Luke 10.20. The Papiſts deny and ſay, we can but haue hope onely, Con. Trid. ſ. 6. c. 9. and yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they confound themſelues, for true hope cannot be deceyued, Rom. 5.5. It is the Anchor of the ſoule, Heb. 6.9. A fift ground is, that wee cannot ſatiſfy God for our leaſt ſinnes: The Scripture aſcribeth all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to Chriſt, He. 1.3. 1. Pet. 1.24. Re. 1.5. The Papiſts maintayn that we may &amp; muſt ſatisfy, making ſatisfaction a part of penance, Con. Trid. ſ. 14. c. 13. A ſixt grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is, that the Scripture containes all doctrine neceſſary for our ſaluation. So ſayth the Scripture, 2. Tim. 3.16. and the ancient Church, Aug. lib. 3. cont. lit. Petil. c. 6. &amp; others. The Papiſts e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall traditions to the Scripture, Con. Trid. ſ. 4. A ſeuenth ground is, that the knowledge of the Scripture is needfull to the people vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, &amp; ought to be read of them. Thereto accords the holy Text, Ioh. 5.39. Col. 3.16. The ignorance therein is the cauſe of all error, Marke 12.24. The Papiſts forbid the people the vſe of the Scripture, Rhemiſts Preface: and do all in the Church ſeruice in an vnknown toung. Eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Scripture teacheth vs to worſhip God alone, Math. 4.10. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts worſhip Angels and Saints, yea their Images &amp; Relikes: Their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia</hi> will not ſerue them: for they pray to crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; that is Latria: and they acknowledge that which they call Latria, to be due to the Croſſe, Tho. p. 3. ſum. Quae. 25. art. 4. &amp; Andrad. lib. 9. Orth. expl. Ninthly, it is the Doctrine of the Scripture, that Chriſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his humane nature, is only in Heauen, Act. 3.21. Papiſts ſay, he is bodily preſent in the Euchariſt, Con. Tri. ſ. 13. ca. 6. Tenthly, Chriſt ordained the Communion in both kinds, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding to do as he did, 1. Cor. 11.24. &amp;c. Papiſts take the Cup from the Laity. Con. Trid. ſ. 21 c. 1. Thus, as in theſe particulars, ſo in many other, it were eaſy to ſhew, how the Church of Rome hath ouerthrowne the maine points of Holy Doctrine, &amp; haue nothing left but the name of the Church, and a Title and ſhewe of Religion.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:20"/>
               <l>Thou fall'ſt now to a rayling vayne,</l>
               <l>And wouldſt by this thy Pope maintayne:</l>
               <l>Leaue idle termes, and ſhew ſome Reaſon,</l>
               <l>Els all theſe wordes come out of ſeaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shew thou what Sects we do deuiſe,</l>
               <l>And wherein we deliuer Lyes:</l>
               <l>And prooue it ſo, that all may ſée,</l>
               <l>Leſt thou thy ſelfe the Lyer bée.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Foxes and Dogges &amp; Wolues thou nam'ſt,</l>
               <l>And Théeues, wherin thy ſelfe thou ſham'ſt:</l>
               <l>Or prooue all this in vs is true,</l>
               <l>Eis we returne it backe to you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They call'd Saint Paul an Heretike, <note n="x" place="margin">Acts 24.14.</note>
               </l>
               <l>A Babbler, <note n="y" place="margin">Acts 17.18.</note> and a Schiſmatike: <note n="z" place="margin">Acts 24.5. &amp; 28.22.</note>
               </l>
               <l>They ſayd, our Sauiour was poſſeſt, <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 8.48.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And of his preaching made a Ieſt, <note n="b" place="margin">Luke 16.14.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet Paul no Hereſy did teach,</l>
               <l>Nor in the Church made any breach:</l>
               <l>Nor yet our Sauiour had a Deuill,</l>
               <l>He neuer did or preached euill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Scripture try wherein we erre,</l>
               <l>We craue no other Arbiter:</l>
               <l>Conuict vs once by ſuch a Iudge,</l>
               <l>We will not at your raylings grudge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now that thy ſtore is almoſt ſpent,</l>
               <l>Thou com'ſt to an old worne Argument:</l>
               <l>Where was your Church ſome yeeres agoe,</l>
               <l>Before the World did Luther know?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:20"/>
               <l>If briefely now I ſhould deny</l>
               <l>The Churches Viſibility:</l>
               <l>It were a word ſufficient,</l>
               <l>To ouerthrow this prattlement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet this I ſay, and will maintaine,</l>
               <l>That euen when Blindneſſe moſt did raine,</l>
               <l>Our Church a certaine beyng had,</l>
               <l>Though not with outward Beauty clad:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like to that holy portion, <note n="c" place="margin">1. Kings 19.8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In that great Superſtition,</l>
               <l>Which ouerwhelm'd all Iſrael,</l>
               <l>After the Tribes from Dauid <note n="d" place="margin">Dauids lyne.</note> fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or as ſome Eares of purer ſeed,</l>
               <l>Amidſt a field of noyſome Weed,</l>
               <l>So God had ſome euen at that time,</l>
               <l>When Antichriſt was in his Prime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now and then out brake the Light,</l>
               <l>Euen in that long and irkſome Night:</l>
               <l>Like as the Sunne in lowring dayes,</l>
               <l>Sometime ſends foorth his glittering rayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long time ere Luther yet was borne,</l>
               <l>Whom you our Founder name in ſcorne,</l>
               <l>There were which ſhew'd their enmyty,</l>
               <l>Againſt your vile Idolatry. <note n="e" place="margin">Bertram wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tranſſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>anno</hi> 812. a Biſhop of Florence was conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for teaching, that Antichriſt was come <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1114. Arnulph was murthered in Rome, for preaching againſt the Pope and his Clergy, <hi>anno,</hi> 1128. Henry, a Monke of Toloſe, was againſt prayer for the dead, pilgrimage, creme oyle, &amp;c. <hi>anno,</hi> 1137. Io. of Salisbury, called the Clergy, Phariſes; the Pope, Antichriſt; and Rome, Babylon, 1151. Gerard and Dulcimus, which taught the Pope to bee Antichriſt, were burnt, with 30. more, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeeres, 1164. 1165. 1166. The Walde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which held in many poynts againſt the Pope, were in <hi>anno,</hi> 1167. &amp; after increaſing in diuers places: Almaris a Biſhop burnt in Paris, for holding againſt Tranſſubſtantiation, Images, Altars, and praying to Saints, 1206. Many in Sueuia did preach the Pope to be an heretike, in the yeres 1236. 1237. 1238. Groſted Biſhop of Lincolne wrote againſt the Pope, <hi>anno</hi> 1246. Arnold <hi>de noua villa,</hi> againſt Maſſes, &amp; Sacrifices for the dead, taught, that the Popes beliefe, was the deuils beliefe, <hi>anno</hi> 1259. All Hiſtories are ful of the like examples. Theſe few may ſerue for a taſte, to ſatiſfie an indifferent Reader, and to ſtop their mouthes, who ſay, none were heard of, of our Religion and Church, till Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19654:21"/>
               <l>But now the Lord hath let vs ſée</l>
               <l>Your Antichriſts deformity,</l>
               <l>That all men might him fully know,</l>
               <l>Before his finall ouerthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Paſtor chiefe <note n="f" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.4.</note> in heauen did ſit,</l>
               <l>And ſo doth ſtil, ſayth holy Writte:<note n="g" place="margin">Acts 4.21.</note>
               </l>
               <l>On earth, a Vniuerſall Prieſt,</l>
               <l>None dare be call'd but Antichriſt. <note n="h" place="margin">Gregory the great, a Biſhop of Rome, ſayd, that whoſo calleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or deſireth to bee called Vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, is the Forerunner of Antichriſt, <hi>Epiſt. ad Eulogium.</hi> lib. 7.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that our Church and Keyes had ſought,</l>
               <l>By tokens in the Scripture tought,</l>
               <l>Our Church and Keyes he might haue found,</l>
               <l>Euen when the world was moſt vnſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Building of Churches nothing makes</l>
               <l>For that which héere thou vndertakes:</l>
               <l>For then commend Demetrius,</l>
               <l>Who builded Shrines at Epheſus.<note n="i" place="margin">Acts 19.24.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well may the Heathen people boaſt</l>
               <l>Of Piramées and Churches coſt:</l>
               <l>In houſes made, God doth not dwell,</l>
               <l>As holy Scripture doeth vs tell. <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 7.48.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neyther all the Churches here,</l>
               <l>Erected by the Papiſts were:</l>
               <l>Nor are by vs aboliſhed</l>
               <l>Places where God is worſhipped.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If priuate men haue euill done:</l>
               <l>For it, blame not Religion:</l>
               <l>Thoſe men which do Church-ſpoyling loue,</l>
               <l>Our Fayth and Church doth not approoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe Celles and Dennes of Idlenes,</l>
               <l>And Nurſeryes of wickedneſſe,</l>
               <l>Vpon good cauſes were diſplac'd,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Baals</hi> Temples were defac'd. <note n="l" place="margin">2. Kings. 10.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Touching Luthers Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note>A Lawleſſe vow <note n="m" place="margin">It is wel called a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Vow, becauſe it is of a thing which is not in mans power. If it be ſaid that by faſting &amp; prayer it may be performed, &amp; continency obtayned: I anſwere, the giftes of God are twofold: Some co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all Beleeuers, as Faith, &amp;c, Some pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to ſome onely, as this of Continency. Now, if by faſting and Praier we labour for the firſt ſort, we ſhal in ſome meaſure receiue them: but we haue not the like aſſurance for the gifts of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort: becauſe (it may be) the Lord is pleaſed otherwiſe to diſpoſe, Now to make ſuch a Vow, is a ſinne: but to perſiſt in it, is a double euill,</note> of ſingle life,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> well brake, and tooke a Wife.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19654:21"/>Better the pure and Spot-leſſe Bed, <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Koite amiantos,</hi> Heb. 13.4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then by vncleane luſtes to be led. <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.9.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Better the marryed Chaſtity, <note n="p" place="margin">Papiſts doe oppoſe mariage &amp; chaſtity: but Paul bids yong women to be chaſte &amp; ſubiect to their Husbands. Tit. 2.4.5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then violent Virginity:</l>
               <l>They ought not ſingle to remaine,</l>
               <l>Who are not gifted, to containe. <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.9.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wedlocke it ſelfe can not defile,</l>
               <l>It hath an Honourable Stile: <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>God doth it not to each man giue,</l>
               <l>Without the marriage bonds to liue. <note n="s" place="margin">Math. 19.11. And it is allowed to a Biſhop, to be the Huſband of one wife, 1. Tim. 3.2.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The forced vowes of Singlenes</l>
               <l>Haue brought foorth beaſtly Filthines:</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt behold in Hiſtory</l>
               <l>The fruits of Monkiſh Lechery. <note n="t" place="margin">There were 6000. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants heads found in Pope Gregory his mote, as appeareth by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Voluntianus, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Carthage, or as ſome thinke, of Hulde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus, Biſhop of Auguſta to Pope Nicholas, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the forbidding of Prieſts mariage.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy poyſoned Tongue doth further reach</l>
               <l>The noble Saxon to impeach:</l>
               <l>Becauſe to Truth he did encline,</l>
               <l>Thou calleſt him a Libertine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When God was pleaſ'd to let him ſée,</l>
               <l>How Chriſt his Death hath made vs frée,</l>
               <l>Then did he déeme it ſlauery,</l>
               <l>To beare the Romiſh tyranny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though Antichriſt did Rome poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">Who kept the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>You kept the Scriptures I confeſſe:</l>
               <l>And in that long Apoſtacy,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Bookes were in your cuſtody.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So I a Pirate falſe haue knowne,</l>
               <l>To kéepe the goods were not his owne,</l>
               <l>And in the Ship to rule and raigne,</l>
               <l>When the right Owner hath bene ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So did the Iewiſh Synagogue</l>
               <l>Safely kéepe Moſes Decalogue,</l>
               <l>And th'other Bookes, <note n="u" place="margin">Viz. the Prophets &amp; Pſalmes; for ſo is the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diuided, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Prophets, and Pſalmes, Luke 24.44.</note> when cruelly</l>
               <l>They did Chriſt Ieſus crucify.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="§" place="margin">Touching the calling of Miniſters.</note>The Paſtors, which did firſt reſtore</l>
               <l>The Trueth which lay long hyd before;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19654:22"/>Thereto were called lawfully,</l>
               <l>And euen by your Authority.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You did them Prieſts and Doctors make,</l>
               <l>And they from you this charge did take, <note n="w" place="margin">In their admittance.</note>
               </l>
               <l>That they the Truth ſhould ſoundly preach,</l>
               <l>And in the ſame the people teach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hereto you cauſed them to ſweare,</l>
               <l>That to the Fayth they ſhould adheare,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſhould errours endure,</l>
               <l>That were againſt the Doctrine pure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That whereunto you did them call,</l>
               <l>Full well they haue performed all:</l>
               <l>Trueth they haue ſought to propagate,</l>
               <l>And Hereſyes to ruinate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As we account your Baptiſme true,</l>
               <l>And neuer do the ſame renue,</l>
               <l>So may you make a lawfull Prieſt,</l>
               <l>Yet be not the pure Church of Chriſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We know that now you wiſer bée,</l>
               <l>And ſweare your Prieſts to Popery, <note n="x" place="margin">In their othes and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, they put in this clauſe (The Catholike and Apoſtolike Church of Rome) which in el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der times was not vſed.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And binde them to maintayne the ſtate</l>
               <l>Of your thrée-Crowned Potentate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sée now (O Papiſt) thou recant,</l>
               <l>Th'art anſwered by a Proteſtant.</l>
               <l>I counſell thée, if thou be wiſe,</l>
               <l>No new euaſions to deuiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy tale of Ethelbert of Kent,</l>
               <l>Is but a ſlender Argument: <note n="y" place="margin">It is alſo anſwered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note>
               </l>
               <l>It ſails not whence the Fayth was brought,</l>
               <l>Or who it firſt amongſt vs tought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let vs into the Scripture looke, <note n="z" place="margin">Iſay 8.20.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And duely ſearch <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 5.39. Acts 17.11.</note> that holy Booke:</l>
               <l>Thence ſhal we know which Church to leaue, <note n="b" place="margin">We haue found Chriſt in the Scriptures; there wee muſt alſo finde the Church, Aug. <hi>de Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>And vnto which alone to cleaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe ſwelling wordes <note n="c" place="margin">2. Pet. 2, 18.</note> of Vnity,</l>
               <l>Succeſſion, and Antiquity,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19654:22"/>Are but poore groundleſſe fantaſyes,</l>
               <l>To blind the ſimple peoples eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though that an Angell thou ſhouldſt ſée,</l>
               <l>Let him (ſayth Paul) accurſed bée, <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>If from the Scripture he doth erre,</l>
               <l>Account him not Gods Miniſter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If one ariſe, and wonders ſhow,</l>
               <l>Séeking the Trueth to ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>Though that might ſéeme a motiue ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Yet vnto him death doeth belong. <note n="e" place="margin">Deut. 13.1, 2, 5.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thréeſcore Byſhops here and thrée,</l>
               <l>Haue bene with vs ſucceſſiuely,</l>
               <l>It eyther prooues our Church is true,</l>
               <l>Or els that marke makes nought for you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Fayth, for which Peter was ſlayne,</l>
               <l>Our Engliſh Church doth ſtill retayne,</l>
               <l>We heare the voyce <note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 10.27.</note> of Chriſt Ieſu,</l>
               <l>Who is the Sonne of God moſt true.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
